A Guide to the Atcheson L. Hench Autograph Collection
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
- Series II: Collection of Modern Autographs
  - 1906 April 9 George Cary Eggleston (1839-1911) to [James Carleton] Young (1856-1918), recommends Henry Holt and Co. to publish the translation of the Life of Tolstoy because "Holt is a scholar, an [author?] and a man unusually appreciative of everything that pertains to scholarship, literature and human advancement. As a publisher he ranks high, and as a man he is one of the salt of the earth.", 3 pages on 1 l. (6435) (Box-folder 7:105)
  - 1906 April 26 George Cary Eggleston (1839-1911) to [James Carleton] Young (1856-1918), says how much he enjoyed reading Mr. [Arthur?] Upson's poem and speaks of sonnets, "The sonnets have not so strongly appealed to me, perhaps because I am unduly exigent in the case of sonnets. The sonnet is the most highly artificial form of literary expression that human ingenuity has invented. As a consequence its only excuse for being is such perfection as shall make the artificial seem natural.", 4 pages on 1 l. (6435) (Box-folder 7:105)
  - 1906 May 31 George Cary Eggleston (1839-1911) to [James Carleton] Young (1856-1918), regrets that he did not receive Arthur Upson's note before he left the city for his country home and had no way to communicate with Upson while he was still in New York, 3 pages on 1 l. (6435) (Box-folder 7:105)
  - 1906 June 25 George Cary Eggleston (1839-1911) to [James Carleton] Young (1856-1918), thanks him for the inscribed copy of Arthur Upson's (1877-1908) book The City: A Poem Drama, 3 pages on 1 l. (6435) (Box-folder 7:105)
  - 1906 September 26 George Cary Eggleston (1839-1911) to [James Carleton] Young (1856-1918), discusses a previous letter of introduction from Young for an unknown person, 1 page, (6435) (Box-folder 7:105)
  - 1906 October 8 George Cary Eggleston (1839-1911) to [James Carleton] Young (1856-1918), recommends that Young's friend send his books to either Bangs or Leavitts for auction and mentions his recent acquisition of A History of the Art of Writing in three vast folio volumes, 7 pages on 2 l. (6435) (6435) (Box-folder 7:105)
  - 1906 November 12 George Cary Eggleston (1839-1911) to [James Carleton] Young (1856-1918), informs him that Mr. [William Dean] Howells has not yet settled in New York and is receiving his mail through Harper & Brothers, 2 pages on 2 l. (6435) (Box-folder 7:105)
  - 1909 May 17 George Cary Eggleston (1839-1911) to [James Carleton] Young (1856-1918), sends an inscribed copy of Two Gentlemen of Virginia back to Young and wishes he could help him on the Mark Twain matter, but "he and I are not on cordial terms, so that any suggestion from me would add to your difficulty instead of relieving it." He also agrees with Young's unfavorable opinion of missionaries., 3 pages on 1 l. (6435) (Box-folder 7:105)
  - 1886 February 23 George Cary Eggleston (1839-1911) to "My Dear Sir," does not believe that he can offer him any employment unless he possesses particular talents that he needs not mentioned in his letter and invites him to call upon himself some day after two o'clock, 1 page (6435) (Box-folder 7:106)
  - 1903 December 14 George Cary Eggleston (1839-1911) Shamrock Card for dinner given to honor him, signed by his friends (6435-g) (Box-folder 7:107)
  - 1894, 1911 George Cary Eggleston (1839-1911) Two Autographs (6435) (Box-folder 7:108)
  - 1903 May 1 George Cary Eggleston (1839-1911) Book Dedication to his wife, Elizabeth (6435) (Box-folder 7:108)
  - 1859 November 15 Charles James Faulkner (1806-1884) to Riggs & Co., encloses a check drawn on the [Valley Bank?] for three hundred dollars (6435) (Box-folder 8:1)
  - 1856 August 15 Charles James Faulkner (1806-1884), House of Representatives, to Robert Tyler (1816-1877), plans on putting Mr. McClanahan's letter before the Democratic Resident Committee at its next meeting and would agree with his proposition at once, except for the problem of the "slow process of the accumulation of funds in the Treasury.", 1 page (6435) (Box-folder 8:2)
  - 1857 May 18 Charles James Faulkner (1806-1884) to [Henry Alexander?] Wise (1806-1876), questions the political motivation behind the recommendations for appointments of the directors of the Valley Bank, 1 page (6435) (Box-folder 8:3)
  - 1860 July 5 Charles James Faulkner (1806-1884), U.S. Minister to France, to the Consuls and Consular Agents of the United States in Egypt and Asia Minor, sends a letter of introduction for the Reverend Cyrus Dickson who will travel in the Middle East, 1 page (6435) (Box-folder 8:4)
  - 1893 April 18 Charles James Faulkner (1847-1929), Senator from West Virginia, to the Superintendent of Admission, Worlds Fair, Chicago, Illinois, thanks for his ticket of admission, 1 page (6435) (Box-folder 8:5)
  - 1897 April 7 Charles James Faulkner (1847-1929), Senator from West Virginia, to the Board of Managers for the National Homes for Disabled Soldiers, endorses Thomas Sykes of Huntington, West Virginia, for one of the "Governor" positions at one of the National Homes for Disabled Soldiers, 1 page (6435) (Box-folder 8:6)
  - 1866 February 1 Philip Ricard Fendall (1794-1868) to William Cabell Rives (1793-1868), sends two numbers of The Congressional Globe containing a debate in the House of Representatives on a Pennsylvania member's discovery that James Madison "had claimed for Congress the Constitutional power to regulate the right of suffrage in the states." 2 pages on 1 l., noted as a draft by Fendall (6435-am) (Box-folder 8:7)
  - 1887 October 25 John Fiske (1842-1901) to General James Grant Wilson (1832-1914), encloses a brief notice of Henry Lee, including a few words about his two sons, possibly for Appleton's Cyclopedia of American Biography edited by the two men, 1 page (6435-as) (Box-folder 8:8)
  - 1835 April 11 John Forsyth (1780-1841), Secretary of State, to S. Hart and others on the committee, regrets the necessity of declining their invitation to join the Democratic citizens of Philadelphia in celebrating the anniversary of the birth of Thomas Jefferson at a public festival on the thirteenth, 1 page (6435) (Box-folder 8:9)
  - 1896 August 23 John Fox, Jr. (1862-1919) to Mr. [Geronime?], promises to stay with him if he makes it to Louisville, Kentucky, in September, and refers to this "silver lunacy" going around the country, 4 pages on 1 l. (6435-az) (Box-folder 8:10)
  - 1966 [September 7] Arlene Francis (1907-2001) to Atcheson Hench (1891-1974), signed typed note with her autograph, 1 page (6435-at) (Box-folder 8:11)
  - 1888 February 15 Mary Eleanor Wilkins Freeman (1852-1930) to Arthur H. Hall, sends her autograph with pleasure, 1 page (6435) (Box-folder 8:12)
  - [1881] January 17 James Anthony Froude (1818-1894) to [James Russell] Lowell (1819-1891), hopes that he can come either on [January] 20th or 21st because Max Muller intended to return to Oxford on January 22. If Lowell must come on January 22, Froude says he will "lock Max Muller in his room and keep him forcibly." He also writes an amusing anecdote about meeting some Tory Members of Parliament at dinner., 4 pages on 1 l. (6435-a) (Box-folder 8:13)
  - 1881 February 7 F[rederick] J[ames] Furnivall (1825-1910), founder of the Browning Society, to Robert Browning (1812-1889), relates a conversation with a bookseller who was convinced that Browning's books would sell like wildfire if there was only a cheap edition available. Furnivall agrees, "I have so long said that the one great hindrance to your popularity is your insisting - or allowing others to insist - on keeping your books dear.", 2 pages on 1 l. (6435-a) (Box-folder 8:14)
  - 1890 February 6 F[rederick] J[ames] Furnivall (1825-1910) to [Robert Barrett Browning] (1849-1912), discusses the objections Browning, Frederic Leighton, and others have expressed about the photogravure made by the Browning Society of Robert Browning; and asks where his grandfather came from in Dorsetshire, so that he can trace the Browning family., 5 pages on 3 l. (6435-a) (Box-folder 8:15)
  - 1864 July 21 F[rederick] J[ames] Furnivall (1825-1910), second editor of the Oxford English Dictionary, to "My dear Sir," works on his project without looking at other dictionaries or any concordance, refers to Blackstone for one definition, 1 page (6435-a) (Box-folder 8:16)
  - 1864 August 4 F[rederick] J[ames] Furnivall (1825-1910) to "My dear Sir," apologizes on finding that "you wanted this [Samuel?] Pegge for yourself; & I have scratched it all about for Dictionary cuttings!" Samuel Pegge (1704-1796) was an antiquary who wrote about English dialects, 1 page (6435-a) (Box-folder 8:17)
  - 1864 August 8 F[rederick] J[ames] Furnivall (1825-1910) to "My dear Sir," He writes "I am immensely obliged to you for your very curious & pretty present of Addisoniana. It is very interesting to see the researches of a hand like his, & the world of letters should be grateful to you for placing them under their sight." He also discusses other work on the Dictionary, 3 pages on 1 l. (6435-a) (Box-folder 8:18)
  - 1844 February 26 Thomas Walker Gilmer (1802-1844), Secretary of the Navy, two days before his death aboard the U.S.S. Princeton, to Representative [Joseph] Grinnell (1788-1885), informs Grinnell that the name of William Henson appeared on the Muster roll of The Dale as having shipped out on October 14, 1841, and paid off and discharged on July 26, 1843, while the ship was at Valparaiso, 1 page (6435) (Box-folder 8:19)
  - 1842 July 25 Thomas Walker Gilmer (1802-1844) to Mr. Williams, promises to take his letter and his case before President John Tyler, 1 page (6435) (Box-folder 8:20)
  - 1841 July 29 Thomas Walker Gilmer (1802-1844) to "Dear Frank," wants his speech on the Tariff, which will be sent to Charlottesville, Virginia, as soon as it is printed, to be seen and read by his constituents as soon as possible; cautions Frank to consult and deliberate well before seeking a candidate to take [Walter?] Cole's place; mentions [William Cabell?] Rives in the Senate; and gives other political advice, 2 pages on 1 l. (6435) (Box-folder 8:21)
  - 1832 October 27 Thomas Walker Gilmer (1802-1844) to the Cashier of the United States Bank, Richmond, Virginia, requests a statement of his account, 1 page (6435) (Box-folder 8:22)
  - ca. 1932 Unpublished hand-written transcript by Robert Gittings (1911-1992) of Anthony and Cleopatra by Chaucer from [Legendary Good Women], 4 pages on 2 l. (6435-af) (Box-folder 8:23)
  - n.d. Ellen Glasgow (1874-1945) to [Miss? Reed], apologizes that every minute of their last few days are filled to the brim but thanks her for her invitation, 2 pages on 1 l. (6435) (Box-folder 8:24)
  - 1919 October 15 Carter Glass (1858-1946), Secretary of the Treasury, to David Singer, thanks for his note expressing his appreciation of Glass' speech at the Credit Section of the Merchants and Manufacturers Association (6435) (Box-folder 8:25)
  - 1857 September 9 Parke Godwin (1816-1904) to "My dear Sir," plans to send his children to his school again during the winter despite the expense, 1 page (6435) (Box-folder 8:26)
  - 1909 June 21 George Washington Goethals (1858-1928) - Special Order concerning John H. Keefe (6435) (Box-folder 8:27)
  - 1897 December 15 Maud Gonne (1866-1953) to Ewan Justice (1875-1922), sends him a pamphlet (not present) by a very distinguished well-known French naval officer, Mr.[Emile?] Duboc lieutenant de vaisseau; the pamphlet caused a sensation in the European press when it was published a year previous and angrily criticized in the English press; she says Duboc is "as hostile to England as I am"; she has marked passages that she deems particularly important and asks if he can get it reviewed in the Post, 3 pages on 1 l. (6435-k) (Box-folder 8:28)
  - 1849 December 10 Josiah Gorgas (1818-1883) to Joseph Hillman, orders leather for one of the United States arsenals, 1 page (6435) (Box-folder 8:29)
  - n.d. Rufus Wilmot Griswold Autograph (6435) (Box-folder 8:30)
  - [1877] July 14 Charles Gounod (1818-1893) to Monsieur Oriolle, in French, traced copy only, original sent to Philip Hench, 1 page (6435) (Box-folder 8:31)
  - 1917 April 3 Percy Aldridge Grainger (1882-1961) to "My dear Mrs. Riggs [Kate Douglas Smith] Riggs [Wiggin?], answers her "sweet and truly kindly letter" she wrote to him after his New York recital with pride at having pleased such a sympathetic artist as Riggs, 3 pages on 1 l. (6435-a) (Box-folder 8:32)
  - 1931 December 18 John W. Haines to [Terence Ian Fitton] Armstrong (1912-1970), refers to his pseudonym John Gawsworth, thanks him for the poems, two of which show his familiarity with his part of the wold, mentions another poet he has taken up [possibly John Skinner (1721-1807)], and plans to meet him if at all possible, 3 pages on 1 l. (6435-bc) (Box-folder 8:33)
  - 1931 December 20 John W. Haines to [Terence Ian Fytton] Armstrong (1912-1970), apologizes about Saturday's plans, none of which worked out due to the illness of his wife and the extremely foggy conditions, 2 pages on 1 l. (6435-bc) (Box-folder 8:33)
  - 1932 November 15 John W. Haines to John Gawsworth [Terence Ian Fitton Armstrong] (1912-1970), writes that he and [William Henry?] Davies spent Saturday "on the top of Dundry beacon 5 miles from Bristol at an old farm house with a young poet named Brian Waters whom Davies likes,", 1 page typewritten (6435-bc) (Box-folder 8:34)
  - 1949 March 14 John W. Haines to John Gawsworth [Terence Ian Fitton Armstrong] (1912-1970), does not object to Gawsworth printing a digest of his article on Robert Frost in "Now and Then" if Jonathan Cape has no objection; catches up on his life events since he last saw him seventeen years ago; mentions his attempt "to get my scattered literary papers together and to put some fragments of memoirs into type: hence my article for Now and Then. Biographers of Davies & Frost are always tapping me for information too. I do not find this easy as I have multitude of letters"; he also mentions the deaths of some of his friends, including [Lascelles] Abercrombie (, Gordon Bottomley (1874-1948), and [William Henry] Davies, "all of whose work I did including getting a printer for his widow. I was at his cremation, but it was in the midst of a bombing raid, telephones were all out of order, the Newport [Conference?] people, among others, couldn't get down and there was only a small congregation, though the service was beautifully taken by his old friend whose name is something like Seagrave.", 2 pages, one typewritten and one hand-written on 1 l. (6435-bc) (Box-folder 8:35)
  - 1931 December 15 John W. Haines to Wilfred W. Gibson (1878-1962), gives advice on the best way for his friend [Terence Ian Fitton Armstrong] to get to the home of [William Henry?] Davies (1871-1940), who was living at "Shenstone," Nailsworth, and mentions meeting poet Cecil Day-Lewis, "he is distinctly good and original,", 1 page typewritten (6435-bc) (Box-folder 8:36)
  - 1901 May 2 Edward Everett Hale (1822-1909) to Mr. Allen, writes "Do you not think that Mr. Conte had better be kept here? I dislike to have him go to New York.", 1 page (6435-ba) (Box-folder 8:37)
  - 1902 January 13 Edward Everett Hale (1822-1909) to Mr. Allen, agrees to speak a few minutes in the evening at their Society if Allen agrees not to release his name in advance because he doesn't want to be inundated with notes from people for whom he has refused to give elaborate evening addresses, 2 typewritten pages on 1 l. (6435-ba) (Box-folder 8:37)
  - 1859 April 22 Edward Everett Hale (1822-1909) to his father, Nathan Hale (1784-1863), writes that he has sent the plants to the freight station addressed to his father and lists the types of plants with their cost minus the shipping, 3 pages on 1 l. (6435) (Box-folder 8:38)
  - n.y. April 9 Edward Everett Hale (1822-1909) to "Dear Williams," regrets that he cannot come to his party on April 13th because he would enjoy meeting Dr. Palmer and thanks him for the "great pleasure we are receiving from the Virgil" which he received as a birthday gift., 2 pages on 1 l. (6435-ba) (Box-folder 8:39)
  - n.y. September 17 Edward Everett Hale (1822-1909) to "Dear Mrs. Williams," "The little book which I send you had its birth one day at your dinner table. It had been planned before but I think you were the first person, outside this house who ever heard of it.", 2 pages on 1 l. (6435-ba) (Box-folder 8:39)
  - 1871 June 16 Edward Everett Hale (1822-1909) to "Dear Harrison," thanks him for the back copies of [Old and New The People's Magazine], "we know no way in which Hurd & Houghton should have had any of our back copies." Also asks when his paper on Methodism for the magazine will arrive., 2 pages on 1 l. (6435-ba) (Box-folder 8:40)
  - n.d. Edward Everett Hale (1822-1909) print made from an engraving (6435-ba) (Box-folder 8:41)
  - [1969] February 21 Nancy Hale (1908-1988) to Atcheson Hench (1891-1974), replies to his mention of seeing a reference to her short story, "Blue-Muslin Sepulcher," originally published in The Ladies Home Journal, concerning the presence of syphilis in a well-bred family in American Story (copy included) and discusses the censorship attitude of the time, 1 typewritten page, with envelope (6435-p) (Box-folder 8:42)
  - 1829 April 28 Anna Maria (Fielding) Hall (1800-1881), Irish novelist, to Mary Russell Mitford (1787-1855), she hopes that "you will find nothing in my Sketches of Irish Character to offend your Political feelings - I can love a Catholic as well as a Protestant, although I think we ought to have kept the upper hand with them"; has just finished her last tale, "Peter the Prophet" for her book last night; plans on spending a few day with her friends, John Carne and his wife, and mentions his Tales of the West (1828), 3 pages on 1 l. (6435-a) (Box-folder 8:43)
  - 1887 November 13 James Orchard Halliwell-Phillips (1820-1889) to Charles Lowe, specifies that he wants popular literature published before 1616, any drawings or engravings of Shakespeare or Stratford-on-Avon localities in the lot purchased at Stratford (although not scenes from the plays), or any old deeds or old manuscript plans of places in Stratford or its neighborhood, 2 pages on 1 l. (6435-a) (Box-folder 8:44)
  - 1884 November 14 James Orchard Halliwell-Phillips (1820-1889) English Shakespearean scholar and collector, to David Nutt, writes that while rarely wanting new foreign books, he does sometimes find English books of interest for sale abroad and old London maps. He particularly wants a series of articles by Dr. L. Ennen on "English Players in Cologne,", 2 pages on 1 l. (6435-a) (Box-folder 8:45)
  - 1846 January 18 James Orchard Halliwell-Phillips (1820-1889) to publisher W[illiam] Shoberl, he sends a copy of the Letters of the Kings, believes the rejected ones very dry letters, but feels Shoberl will find "a large number of very readable" letters from those sent, 2 pages on 1 l. (6435) (Box-folder 8:46)
  - 1780 [May 17] James I. Hamilton (d.1803), Brigadier General of the British army, captured at Saratoga, commanded the 21st Foot (Scots Fusiliers) - Autograph on a financial document, a check endorsed by him at Charlottesville, 1 page (6435) (Box-folder 8:47)
  - n.d. Joel Chandler Harris Autograph (6435) (Box-folder 8:48)
  - 1881 August 20 Paul Hamilton Hayne (1830-1886) to Mr. [F.H.?] Allen, inquires about his health and expresses concern over his illness, especially in the severe heat. Augusta, Georgia, actually experienced three days when the temperature was above 95 degrees, 2 pages on 1 l., with typed transcript (6435) (Box-folder 8:49)
  - n.d. Paul Hamilton Hayne (1830-1886) to Mr. Bowen, asks if he is still the poet critic for The Independent and sends him a copy of his "Savannah Sesqui-Centennial Ode" which has never before been correctly printed. He wants Bowen to read "the parts concerning the career and characters of Oglethorpe, a grand man, not half appreciated by Historians, who are too often a set of solemn and pretentious owls!", 1 page, with typed transcript (6435) (Box-folder 8:50)
  - 1880 August 18 Paul Hamilton Hayne (1830-1886) to Mr. Brainerd, encloses a poem "The Constitution," and asks that it be carefully proof-read "since the piece is one of these sure to be ruined by any verbal errors in print", 2 pages on 1 l. (6435) (Box-folder 8:51)
  - 1882 June 26 Paul Hamilton Hayne (1830-1886) to Mr. Brainerd, thanks him for sending a proof of his article about his poems now being published by Lothrop & Co. and congratulates him upon his marriage, 1 page (6435) (Box-folder 8:51)
  - 1882 August 14 Paul Hamilton Hayne (1830-1886) to Mr. Brainerd, sends along a poem for his journal and asks for 12-15 copies of "Constitution" to be sent to him, 1 page (6435) (Box-folder 8:51)
  - 1879 February 10 Paul Hamilton Hayne (1830-1886) to [Hezekiah] Butterworth (1839-1905), informs him that he does not need to pay for the use of "The Chameleon" because he intended the prose anecdotes as "free-offerings"; considers him lucky to have secured Whipple as a contributor, as he is "one of the ablest aesthetic critics in America; refers to the death of Richard Henry Dana; offers some more verses for The Youth's Companion, and asks if he received Timrod's autograph note from Hayne's wife, 2 pages on 1 l. (6435) (Box-folder 8:52)
  - 1882 March 29 Paul Hamilton Hayne (1830-1886) to Messrs. Charles Scribner & Son, sends a postal card note to say he has received the copy of Tennyson's poems, 1 page (6435) (Box-folder 8:53)
  - 1882 November 2 Paul Hamilton Hayne (1830-1886) to "Gentlemen and Friends" his publisher [D. Lothrop and Company] expresses his appreciation for the fine work done by them on his book Poems of Paul Hamilton Hayne and asks that they send immediately the copies ordered by Major Hill, as agent, since he cannot order more books until he has delivered those already ordered., 2 pages on 1 l., with typed transcript (6435) (Box-folder 8:54)
  - 1886 January 22 Paul Hamilton Hayne (1830-1886) to Mrs. Dickinson, thanks her profusely for her gift of silk handkerchiefs and autographs a photograph for her upon the back as his ink will not penetrate the surface of the photograph, 2 pages on 1 l. (6435) (Box-folder 8:55)
  - 1877 January 24 Paul Hamilton Hayne (1830-1886) to A.H. Dooley, "Opera House Bookstore," notifies him that he did receive the letter and post card but was prevented in answering by the severe illness of his wife, 2 pages on 1 l. with envelope, with typed transcript (6435) (Box-folder 8:56)
  - 1880 September 2 Paul Hamilton Hayne (1830-1886) to Mrs. Harris, promises to mail her the article about [Joaquin] Miller in a week and compares him unfavorably with Sidney Lanier, who "is every inch a gentleman, and has far more subtlety of mind than 20 Millers rolled into one!!! Look at his superb Marshes of Glynn!" 2 pages on 1 l., with typed transcript (6435) (Box-folder 8:57)
  - 1871 November 27 Paul Hamilton Hayne (1830-1886) to Dr. Josiah Gilbert Holland (1819-1881), asks Holland to please continue to send him Scribner's Magazine [free?] since as Literary Editor of the Augusta Constitutionalist and a contributor to many other Southern papers, he has spoken highly of Holland's magazine and has attempted to extend its circulation in the South. 2 pages on 1 l., with typed transcript (6435) (Box-folder 8:58)
  - 1867 August 2 Paul Hamilton Hayne (1830-1886) to Hurd & Houghton, thanks them for regularly sending "London Society" and "The Monthly for Young People," as well as their new books; mentions that he now edits the Literary department of the Southern Opinion, Richmond where some of their works have already received notice; and shares his plan to draw special attention to the Hurd and Houghton firm in an article by himself, 2 pages on 1 l., with typed transcript (6435) (Box-folder 8:59)